[Music]
I'm Sarah sharp I'm a deal attorney that
specializes in people buying and Salen
County practices and this is my weekly
windown where I talk about a theme of
the week while I open a bottle of
wine at the end of course of my week now
now this week is a holiday week and I am
about to go ride my mountain bike so I
did not want to drink actual wine or
alcoholic wine but this is alcohol-free
wine so the wine this week is can you
see it is called groovy g r uvi dry SEO
I ordered at a restaurant for the first
time not too long ago and the people I
was with didn't know that I was drinking
a non-alcoholic prco and one of them
even tasted it and didn't realize that
it was not alcoholic which which is
great so the tasting notes it's inspired
by the effervescence of champagne it is
delicious carbonated wine crafted from
wine grapes so that doesn't really tell
us much does it floral and tart and
notes so let's see if that's true it's a
hot day
so I mean honestly very similar to
alcoholic champagne so I don't know if
you would get a headache the next
morning if you drank a bunch of these or
not the theme this week that I've
thought of over and over again is
exclusivity for some of you who don't
know accounting practice it's a very
seasonal m&a cycle so in the tax season
essentially January February March April
nothing's happening May people staying
in a wall June you get some listings
there's a lot of activity and the
letters of intent or offers July some
people have chosen letters of intent to
go down the road with and I've had a
couple closings but we'll get more and
more towards the end of July and a lot
more in August and September and things
styal back a little bit the September
15th October 15th deadlines you're
straight into Thanksgiving Christmas and
then you're back in the next tax season
so it's busy busy busy time for me and
for my clients to be doing buying and
selling of accounting practices
exclusivity hold
on this is genuinely really good and you
can order it on Amazon you know have to
sign for it to get delivered which it's
convenient for a busy professional you
should you should try getting your
non-alcoholic beverage just delivered by
Amazon exclusivity is often in letters
of intent which just a really back up if
you're looking to buy an accounting
practice you're looking at listings
usually on um some of the aggregator
sites like accounting practice exchange
or bis by sell you might be enrolled in
some of kind of newsletter type of
things that different Brokers have to
notify you about new listings of new
accounting practices for sale if that
happens and you reach out for
information on a listing they're likely
going to get you to sign in NDA so look
at my deal Academy course on
non-disclosure agreements because I
think that you would believe the things
that I see in a non-disclosure agreement
where the things that are missing
they're not all created equal certainly
read it before you sign it but you'll
sign an NDA you'll usually talk to the
broker and get some questions answered
they might even have you talk to the
seller to just kind of get a temperature
read on whether you'd be a good fit and
then they're going to say all right give
us your letter of intent a lot of times
that's the first time somebody reaches
out to me because they say oh shoot I
need some kind of legal document drafted
I like that reach out to me it at that
point is fantastic equally likely or
only slightly less uh common I have
people who have already gone through
that process of the letter of intent and
then reach out to me and that's a harder
position to be in from a negotiating
perspective then you're looking at your
letter of intent lots of terms in a
letter of intent you know check out my
course on letters of inal Academy if you
want I won't go into all that the one
that really I have had the most mixed
feelings about is the term for
exclusivity where you say hey I'm
looking to buy your firm if you're going
to talk to me I I want you to only talk
to me for the next 30 60 90 days pretty
standard to do that across Industries
but it's so different the impact is so
powerfully different in such a seasonal
business because if you lock someone up
right now in July for 60 days then the
deal falls through if they're going to
be listing they're company again it's
going to be in the fall when there's way
less activity far fewer buyers the
likelihood that they get it sold this
year goes down substantially so these
are the most significant 306090 days so
I'm not crazy about agreeing to very
long exclusivity on the sellers side
obviously on the buyer side it's like
get as long as you can get but if you're
the seller you want to restrict that as
much as possible and a lot of times this
kind of obligation to be
exclusive comes with a good faith
deposit so you'll see those together a
lot in the writing it'll say like I'm
looking at one on my screen right now
this say exclusive negotiations and good
faith deposit and then there's a
paragraph that says once you execute
this buyer will provide $25,000 to
Escrow the good faith deposit and during
the 60 you know 30 60 90day period
following the date um of the signature
here too and until closing unless buyer
indicates it's not willing to blah blah
blah then you'll be exclusive and that
can be a really long agreement it can be
a couple sentences I have not died on
the hill of exclusivity in the past
people might watch this that I've had
this conversation with I haven't
historically seen the value in the good
faith deposit especially because the
standard is that if you call off the
deal for any reason you get that deposit
back it has felt like a silly kind of
extra admin type step to take that might
slow things down and kind kind of crunch
them up so I haven't been crazy about
good faith deposits but I also you know
I usually have advised buyers like you
get it back either way so what's what's
the downside this is great
also there's some Brokers that will say
I've never done a single deal I've never
done a single deal that as exclusivity
and I never will and they're probably
being honest you know who knows I have
never told people to break a deal it
because the seller is unwilling to
exclusive I've never told um buyers
don't give good faith deposit I've never
told sellers demand good faith deposit
because I see all sides of the issue
it's at such a low purchase price
usually where I'm working that we're
talking about a sub $2,000 kind a deal
fee usually and nobody's going to able
to afford to sue over that the legal
cost would way outpace the amount in
question if you can't enforce it what's
the point of fighting over it and
frankly it's a deal term that I don't
really usually want my clients to waste
time on I don't want them to waste
negotiating capital on because it's not
a deal term for the ultimate deal it's a
shortterm deal term anyways that's
historically been my really agnostic
type of it's good it's bad if you want
it we can do it type of thing but more
recently I have started to think about
it differently one value that having a
completely refundable a goodfaith
deposit brings that is so substantial
and that had frankly overlooked a little
bit is that it encourages the buyer to
admit when they are done with the deal
so if you have
$25,000 tied up in a potential practice
that you thought about buying you've
lost enthusiasm for the practice you're
probably going to be motivated to tell
the seller I decided to go a different
direction can I have my money back and
unfortunately because the window to sell
is so narrow I've had so many buyers
lose enthusiasm for a deal maybe their
own personal circumstances change maybe
they didn't realize what they were
getting into and they're realizing it
more and more and more there's so many
different things that can happen where
maybe the time just passes so it's
suddenly running their own practice and
they're getting you know distracted by
like extension filing deadlines and
stuff like that it makes them come to
terms with the fact that they're not
going to proceed with the deal and it
makes them be honest about that and let
the seller know so the seller then can
break up with the exclusivity Clause if
it's drafted right and can go back on
the market sooner rather than later I
have changed my mind and now I'm in
favor I think pretty sure in most cases
of at least a good face deposit
certainly where there's exclusivity I
want a good faith deposit if I'm
representing the seller especially I
want that good faith deposit because I
want them to tell us if they've gone a
different direction it's not uncommon
and there's nothing wrong with a buyer
pursuing multiple deals there shouldn't
be anything wrong with a seller pursuing
a couple buyers until you sign the
letter of intent and agree to
exclusivity so we just really want to
make sure that everyone is focused on
that one deal at that time and honest
and motivated to let you know as soon as
possible if that's not going to keep
going that's the big deal I mean at this
point in my career it's pretty exciting
when I get to think about a new angle on
one of the terms in a letter of intent
so cheers exclusivity and good faith
deposits this has been a weekly wind
down if you found this valuable at all
bless you please like And subscribe to
our YouTube channel I really appreciate
it
[Music]